<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ad clerum a visitation sermon preached at Beckonsfield in the county of Bucks, April the 9th, 1678 / by John James ...</title>
            <author>James, John, b. 1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35427</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15294354</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15294354</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103379</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46626)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103379)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1190:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ad clerum a visitation sermon preached at Beckonsfield in the county of Bucks, April the 9th, 1678 / by John James ...</title>
                  <author>James, John, b. 1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 45 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.H. for R. Chiswel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, IV, 1-2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103379:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AD CLERUM. A VISITATION SERMON PREACHED At <hi>Beckonsfield</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks, April</hi> the 9<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOHN JAMES, <hi>A. M. Rector of</hi> Latimers <hi>in the County of</hi> Bucks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.H.</hi> for <hi>R. Chiſwel,</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in St. <hi>Paul's Church-yard,</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:103379:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur, <hi>Geo. Thorp.</hi> R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> in C.P.D. Domino <hi>Gulielmo</hi> Archiep. <hi>Cant.</hi> a Sacris Domeſticis.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 31. 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103379:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 4.1, 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let a man ſo account of us, as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Myſteries of God. Moreover it is required in Stewards, that a man be found faithful.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SAint <hi>Paul</hi> having planted Chriſtianity among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> by preaching the Goſpel of Chriſt in the City of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and other adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Provinces in the Countrey of <hi>Greece;</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſpace of Eighteen Months he departed from thoſe Regions, and took his Journey into <hi>Aſia,</hi> where he alſodelivered what he had received from the Lord, and inſtructed the People both publickly in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and privately in their Houſes, in the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Kingdom of God: Immediately after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, <hi>Apollos</hi> being by <hi>Priſcilla</hi> and <hi>Aquila,</hi> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently inſtructed in the Doctrine of the Goſpel upon his coming to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> is by them recommended and ſent to the Brethren at <hi>Achaia,</hi> where he boldly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and diligently taught the things of the Lord; confirming thoſe who were converted by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the grounds and principles of the Chriſtian faith, and by arguments unanſwerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing the moſt obſtinate <hi>Jews,</hi> and putting to ſilence publickly in the Synagogues the moſt ſubtle and ſhrewdeſt Diſputants among them, <hi>Acts</hi> 18. <hi>verſ.</hi> 24 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though <hi>Paul</hi> had planted the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103379:3"/>in converting many by the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to be Proſelytes to it, and <hi>Apollos</hi> after him, had wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered thoſe Converts, in contributing his utmoſt aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to ſettle and eſtabliſh them on the Foundation which <hi>Paul</hi> had laid, though God himſelf had given increaſe in making their labours effectual by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed influence of his Spirit, to obtain thoſe great ends he deſigned, in the promulgation of the Goſpel; to wit, the Converſion and Edification of Souls, in the faith of Chriſt; yet, in a ſhort time the heat of their Devotion began to be abated, or rather to be miſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed upon improper objects: For thoſe which had enrolled themſelves into the ſame Society, profeſſed and were Baptized into the ſame faith; and ſo became mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame myſtical body; broke forth into furious contentions &amp; animoſities againſt each other, rendring moſt miſerably, and moſt cruelly tearing the Church of Chriſt to pieces in its very Infancy; for through the enmity of thoſe impure <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> againſt the Rules and Precepts of Chriſtianity, and the malice of the Judaizing Chriſtians, againſt many points of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine contained therein; moſt lamentable Schiſms and Factions broke forth in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> which like flames of Fire were ready to conſume and burn it down to the ground; Errors and Hereſies were ſcattered abroad, and greedily received by too many among them, which like ill Weeds ſoon grew up, and brought forth moſt unwholſom fruit in their lives and manners.</p>
            <p>This ſad news no ſooner came to the Ears of our Apoſtle, but it ſunk heavily down upon his Soul, and made a deep impreſſion of ſorrow upon his minde; therefore to redreſs theſe miſchiefs, and if poſſible, to ſettle the diſtractions and diviſions of <hi>Corinth,</hi> he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103379:3"/>preſently compoſeth and directs this Epiſtle to the Church there, and to all other Chriſtians both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> inhabiting the Regions of <hi>Achaia,</hi> in which after a Religious and moſt affectionate Salutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to procure from them a favourable Audience, and a candid entertainment of what he delivered, from <hi>v.</hi> 1. to <hi>v.</hi> 9. He moſt earneſtly exhorts them to an Unity in Doctrine and brotherly Communion one among ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>verſ.</hi> 10, 11. And then laying open before their eyes the grievouſneſs of their Schiſm, he charges them boldly with it to their very faces, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11, 12, 13. Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them plainly that the Chriſtian Religion is but one, and Chriſt Jeſus the only Author of it: That the excellency of its is ſuch, that though it be not uſhered into the World with ſublimity of ſpeech, and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of humane wiſdom, and therefore is ſtyled the fooliſhneſs of Preaching, and by the learned Scribes, and wiſe Diſputers of the World, was reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with pride and inſolence; yet, it conſiſteth in the power of God, and ſo far excelleth the wiſdom of this World, that it deſtroys the underſtanding of the Wiſe and Prudent, and confounds the things that are Mighty and Noble: Chap. 1.2. That as Chriſt is the Author of this Divine Inſtitution, ſo he is the only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Foundation for men to lay the Superſtructure of their Faith and Salvation upon; and according to the expreſſion of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> Acts 4.12. <hi>The only Name un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven given among Men, whereby they ſhould be called:</hi> And conſequently that thoſo who labour in the Church of Chriſt, have no dominion over the Faith of men, or authority to command their Conſciences; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they are Miniſters of Chriſt, and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labourers together with God: Stewards in the Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith, and Diſpenſers of the Myſteries of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103379:4"/>Goſpel; and therefore as men are obliged to ſhew them their reſpective and juſt eſteem, but not to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend its preſcribed limits and bounds, ſo 'tis required theſe be faithful in their Office, and Conſcientious in the diſcharge of ſo Sacred a Function: which as 'tis a prevalent means to repair the breaches and cure the diviſions in the Church of Chriſt, ſo 'tis the advice of the Apoſtles to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and the immediate deſign of the words in my Text. <hi>Let a man ſo account of us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That my diſcourſe may be full and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, proportionable to the juſt deſign and import of theſe words; and ſerviceable in ſome meaſure to the preſent occaſion, and future neceſſities of this Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; Three things neceſſarily require our conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, The Subjects of the Apoſtles diſcourſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed under the Pronoun, <hi>Us.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter predicated of, or attributed to theſe Perſons: <hi>The Miniſters of Chriſt and Stewards of the Myſteries;</hi> both which Particulars joyned together, make up an entire Propoſition; that the Perſons intended by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>are the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, Practical Inferences deduced from the truth of the Apoſtles aſſertion, one reſpecting the men to whom theſe perſons are employed as <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Stewards: Let a man ſo account of us, as of—</hi> The other relating to the Perſons themſelves, to whom their Office is committed. <hi>Moreover 'tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in Stewards, that a man be found faithful.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, We ſhall conſider the ſubjects of the Apoſtles diſcourſe, implyed under the Pronoun, <hi>Us:</hi> The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons here intended, being the very Foundation of the Apoſtles Argument, and a juſt determination of this Particular, the moſt regular and orderly Method to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103379:4"/>aſſiſt us in the undertaking, and progreſs of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent employment. 'Tis certain, that the Perſons ſpoken of, whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> did directly and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpect are thoſe mentioned, Chap. 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>Paul, Apollos</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> who were ſeparated by the Lord for the work of the Miniſtry, and appointed as ſubſervient to the Faith and Salvation of the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> but that this particular direction to the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> may be of larger uſe and ſervice to the Church of Chriſt in general, 'tis moſt rational and conſentaneous to the whole ſcope and tenure of the Goſpel, to affirm, that all thoſe, who according to the Canons of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, are conſecrated to the ſame imployment, are inveſted with the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Office, implicitely included in the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apoſtle, and therefore as juſtly ſtyled, Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Goſpel, as <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollos</hi> or <hi>Cephas</hi> were.</p>
            <p>And if particular Commiſſion be neceſſary to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the Offices of the holy Order, the Negative holds as infallibly true as the Affirmative, that no perſon may preſume to adminiſter any Office appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate to this ſacred Function, but thoſe who are Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally called to, and Canonically inveſted with it: for the Goſpel, almoſt as oft as occaſion is offered to make mention of the Miniſters and diſpenſers of it, plainly intimates, that the Maſter of our Religion, deſigns a ſeparation of perſons from ſecular employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to officiate in the Miniſtry and Preaching of the Goſpel, as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. The Apoſtle reſembles the Church to a Body, which is conſtituted of ſeveral Members, and every one deſigned to ſerve in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place for the benefit and advantage of the whole; that the foot cannot uſurp the Office of the Head, nor
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103379:5"/>the Arm exerciſe the Authority of the Brain; but every one diſcharge its proper Function; that there be no Schiſm nor Diviſion in the body; in proportion to which ſimilitude the ſtate of Chriſt's myſtical body is to be underſtood, in which every the meaneſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is a Member in particular, but every Member can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſpose and regulate the affairs of the whole; <hi>For are all Apoſtles? are all Prophets? are all Teachers? do all ſpeak with Tongues? do all Interpret?</hi> Verſ. 29.30. <hi>Shall the foot ſay, Unleſs I am head, I will not be of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? Or the ear ſay, Becauſe I am not the eye, I am not ſufficiently honored? If the whole Body were an eye, where were the hearing? And if every Member were the Head, where were the Body? But God hath ſet the Members every one in the Body as it hath pleaſed him,</hi> Verſ. 16, 17, 18.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt Apoſtles,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondarily Prophets,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly Teachers,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
Verſ. 28. And that this diſtinction ſhould remain in the Church to the end of the World, is confidently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffirmed by the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. Wherein he declares, that the Officers of the Church therein mentioned to be given for the perfecting of the Saints, for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which Phraſes muſt of neceſſity denote their continuance in the Church, till the number of Gods Elect are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and the ſtate of Chriſts myſtical Body perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compleated; and for this reaſon St. <hi>Paul</hi> juſtifies his ſpecial deſignation to the Apoſtleſhip, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts his <hi>Presbyters</hi> to continual dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in their imployment, as their proper and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duty, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2.</p>
            <p>And inded if we ſearch into the ancient Records of the World; or conſider the account, which Modern Hiſtorians have privately collected, and publickly preſented to us, the moſt learned and faithfull among
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103379:5"/>them, do confidently aſſure us, that never any Nation in the World, made a publick profeſſion of Religion, but the Governours thereof ſolemnly appointed a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Perſons, whoſe conſtant employment it ſhould be to Solemnize and Celebrate the Myſteries thereof; and <hi>Moſes</hi> in tranſcribing the Hiſtory of the Church of God, both before and after the Floud, and under the admiſtration of the Law, hath recorded the obſervation of the ſame cuſtom, in thoſe ſeveral forms of Church-government; thus <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> were Preachers of Righteouſneſs to the old World; <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and the ſucceeding Patriarchs were Kings and Prieſts, in their reſpective Families, and duly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred the affairs of Religion to their ſeveral charges: And when God erected his Theocratical Government over the <hi>Jews,</hi> whom he had choſen for his own Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he commanded <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons to be ſet apart for the Prieſts Office, that they might wait at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of the Lord, and Miniſter to the People in Holy things, which was appointed a Statute unto him, and to his Seed after him for evermore, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.1, 43.</p>
            <p>And if the Chriſtian Religion muſt be denyed this honour, and no ſuch Cuſtom obſerved in the Church of Chriſt; this ſtrange innovation muſt be grounded upon one or both of theſe reaſons, either that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains matters of leſs value and concernment to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, than the Religion of other Nations to the Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes of it: Or elſe that they are ſo plain eaſie in all and every particular Doctrine, that the meaneſt underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding can comprehend their moſt intimous ſence and meaning, and 'tis impoſſible for the moſt illiterate to be deceived in his judgment concerning them. Theſe are the faireſt pretences that can be alledged againſt the neceſſary diſtinction of the Miniſterial Office, yet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103379:6"/>their weakneſs is apparent at the firſt view, and their abſurdity ſo groſs, that it may palpably be felt: For the Goſpel of Chriſt is ſo far from deſerving this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and contempt, that it contains matters of the greateſt moment and importance for Man to know; ſuch as are the excellency of the Divine Nature, the ſtate and condition of mans Soul; and that incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Method contrived by the Divine Wiſdom for mans eternal happineſs; comprehends matters of the moſt univerſal Satisfaction to the minds of men, and propounds the duties of a Practical Religion, which are moſt agreeable to the Divine Nature to require, and moſt reaſonable for Mankind to obſerve; in all which reſpects it infinitely tranſcends all the Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms of Religion entertain'd in the World, and even the worſhip of the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves; and though thoſe Practical points which are eſſentially neceſſary to mans Salvation, are extremely ſuitable to the dictates of right reaſon, and delivered with the greateſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuity and clearneſs imaginable; yet, it diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth concerning points of Faith, of the greateſt depth and myſteriouſneſs which are altogether inconceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and incomprehenſible, and do exceed the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of any created Being; ſuch are the Eternal purpoſes and decrees of God; the Doctrine of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Incarnation of the Son of God, with other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of like affinity, ſcattered up and down the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; for ſo St. <hi>Peter</hi> tell us, That in the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> are ſome things hard to be underſtood, which they that are unlearned and unſtable ſo wreſt, as they do alſo the other Scriptures to their own deſtruction, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. What can be ſpoken of ſuch infinite importance? What can be delivered of ſo tremendous conſequence, as the Chriſtian Religion? And ſhall not the ſacred
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103379:6"/>Offices of ſo Divine an Inſtitution<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be handled with the moſt awful Solemnity, and Celebrated with the greateſt reverence and moſt Religious adoration imaginable? And when many ſtumble at this Rock of offence and miſcarry at the ſight of thoſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull things repreſented therein, is it not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely neceſſary that men of the greateſt wiſdom and gravity be Conſecrated for the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry; that they may improve their time and abilities for a right underſtanding of the Myſteries of the Chriſtian Faith, and then employ the Talent of their Wiſdom and Knowledge, for the information and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of others; that men may not promiſcuouſly intermeddle with thoſe Holy Offices, nor any man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſtricteſt diſtinction of Paſtour and People: go aſtray through want of inſtruction, and periſh for want of underſtanding?</p>
            <p>But becauſe the ſubject of our preſent Argument reſpects a Matter of Fact; and to diſcourſe only <hi>de Jure</hi> concerning the Ordinances of Chriſt is inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to our preſent purpoſe; let us conſider what the Maſter of our Religion hath <hi>de facto</hi> determined concerning the Miniſterial Office; the firſt remarkable Inſtance that affords any light to this diſquiſition, is the Election and nomination of Apoſtles, recorded <hi>Mark</hi> 3.13. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.13. Whoſe Commiſſion is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their Lord and Maſter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.1. After this, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.1. <hi>He called his Seventy Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to whom he gave Commiſſion to Preach the Goſpel;</hi> theſe were the only Perſons which that ſupreme Head of the Church Ordained in Perſon; and to theſe he gave Commiſſion to execute the Miniſterial Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, as their proper and peculiar Function; the Twelve Apoſtles, and the Seventy-two Diſciples:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103379:7"/>And that theſe ſacred Orders might remain in the Church to the end of the World; when he firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to an Aſſembly of his Apoſtles, after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, he breathed on them the Holy Ghoſt, and thereby inveſted them with full Authority to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Paſtoral Office, for the Ordering and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning his Church, which his Father had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21, 22. <hi>As my Father hath ſent me, even ſo ſend I you;</hi> which immediately before his Aſſention he again renews, with a plain intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the continuance of that Order; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the neceſſity of Ordaining men to ſucceed them in it, till all things ſhould be fulfilled, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20.</p>
            <p>And that the Apoſtles underſtood their Maſter in this ſence is apparent, becauſe as neceſſity required through the death of the preſent Officers or the larger groweth and extent of the Church, they Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together, and exerciſed Epiſcopal Authority in Ordaining others to that Holy employment. Thus they Conſecrated <hi>Matthias,</hi> though he were Elected by God himſelf, into the place of <hi>Judas,</hi> and he was numbered with the Eleven Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.25. And though St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a ſingular Inſtance of an immediate miraculous Call, when by a voice from Heaven he was made an Apoſtle; yet, he began not to Preach the Goſpel, till <hi>Ananias</hi> had put his hands on him, and prayed over him, that he might be filled with the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.17. And when the <hi>Gentiles</hi> had received the Goſpel through the diſperſion of the Chriſtians upon the proſecution of St. <hi>Stephen;</hi> the Apoſtles remaining ſtill at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſent forth <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> that he ſhould go to <hi>Antioch,</hi> who finding <hi>Saul</hi> at <hi>Tarſus,</hi> joyned together, and mightily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103379:7"/>the Believers there, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. And in the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapter, theſe Two men were ſolemnly Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Apoſtles of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> by thoſe Apoſtolical Perſons mentioned, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1 To all which agrees that Rule of the Apoſtle, compriſed in the Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 10.15. <hi>How ſhall they Preach except they be ſent? (i.e.)</hi> They have no Authority, and can expect no bleſſing upon their labours, till they have a lawful Commiſſion to ſet them on work. To which practice of the Apoſtles, the Primitive, and all ſucceding Churches in Chriſtendom, till ſome Zealots of late, have juſtly confirmed, as all Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al Hiſtories do fully teſtifie; and thus St. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens,</hi> contemporary, with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> hath left on Record:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> That the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles firſt Ordained Miniſters in Churches, and gave command, that as any were removed by death, the moſt deſerving Perſons ſhould be Choſen into their place, and Ordained to execute their Office. Now certainly, the Example and approbation of ſo great a Cloud of Witneſſes, is not only a ſufficient Warrant, but a juſt Authority to regulate the affairs of the Church, according to their Pattern, to the Worlds end. So that I may lawfully aſſume my deſigned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and confidently deliver it as a juſt and regular Concluſion, that whatever Perſons have been ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively Ordained into, or at preſent inveſted with the Sacred Order of the Miniſterial Office, by impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands from Regular Biſhops and their <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> ſuch men from the Authority of Apoſtolical pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, are to all intents all purpoſes the Miniſters of Chriſt, and moſt properly Stewards of the Goſpel; and that all other perſons, whatever be their Natural abilities, their Supernatural Graces, their acquired
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103379:8"/>parts, or their great experience in Church-affairs, have lot or portion as Agents in theſe matters, till they receive Commiſſion from good Authority; and which is more conſiderable, do willfully caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of the Church of Chriſt, whilſt they reject and diſown his lawfull Miniſters; which was the Judgment of that moſt ancient Father, St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Trall. P. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So that it was not without great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that that bleſſed Martyr called upon the Church of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> with ſuch zeal and importunity.<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lad. P. <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we then think of the inſolence of thoſe men, who Sacrilegiouſly uſurp the Miniſterial Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, being neither ſent by men, nor as they pretend, called by God? I mean thoſe illiterate, but conceited Mechanicks, who being ingaged in ſome civil Calling as the buſineſs and employment o their lives preſume to be Maſters of Divinity, and Teachers in the buſineſs of Religion; as if Divine Knowledge were in this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and declining age of the World, conveyed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the minds of men, by the working of Miracles, through an immediate inſpiration; or the Sacred My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Chriſtianity were expoſed by Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Guardian to the open World, to be proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to, and deſecrated by any the moſt common or unſanctified Perſons. 'Tis true that the Prophecies of the Old Teſtament might be fulfilled, and to illuſtrate the glory of the New; in the beginning of the Chriſtian World, God did communicate extraordinary gifts, even to mean and ordinary perſons, who being inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt did extraregularly Propheſie, or Interepret, or ſpeak with Tongues, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.17. For ſo it was ſpoken
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103379:8"/>By the Prophet, <hi>Joel.</hi> 2.28. But as they were but few, beſide the Officers of the Church, to whom God diſpenſed thoſe miraculous gifts, ſo they did not pretend to aſſume the Miniſterial Office, nor preſume to execute any part thereof, but only altered the inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Dictates of the Holy Ghoſt, for which their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary endowments were a ſufficient Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and when thoſe ceaſed, the men returned to their former condition.</p>
            <p>And 'tis agreed by all, that there are but two ways, by which men may enter into the Office Miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, by immediate Command from God, or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Commiſſion from men; at the firſt Plantation of the Goſpel, thoſe extraordinary Miniſters were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their Function by an extraordinary Call from Heaven; but becauſe God cannot work in vain, and will not multiply Miracles without juſt neceſſity; that other Method of initiating Church-Officers, is by Divine appointment eſtabliſhed in the Church, I mean the Impoſition of hands with the prayers of the Superiour Clergy, which Form as 'tis more ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry than the former, ſo 'tis ſufficient for its purpoſe, and fairly correſpondent to the perpetual Rules of a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and eſtabliſhed Religion; the former Miniſters gave evidence of their Ordination by their miraculous Operations; the latter muſt if at all, by the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials of the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> of whom they are ordained: therefore I cannot but ask thoſe bold Pretenders, by what Authority they exerciſe thoſe ſtrange and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular courſes, and who gave them that Authority, that ſix days in the week they ſhall labour and do all that they have to do in their Secular employments; and behold on the Seventh, they ſit as Maſters of Aſſemblies, or ſtand forth as Preachers in a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103379:9"/>if they receive their power from God, let them come forth and produce their evidences; let them in the name of Chriſt do wonders, and work Miracles, then we will imbrace them as Apoſtles, and give them the right hand of fellowſhip; otherwiſe 'tis certain, they are not the Meſſengers of God; if they derive it from men, I ask from whom? From the Biſhops and <hi>Presbyters?</hi> Who are intruſted with the Office of Ordination, as being competent Judges of the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of men for Spiritual Miniſtries? If not from them, they are Invaders and Intruders into the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the Church, and in the language of Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Thieves and Robbers,</hi> Joh. 10.1. But if they will uſurp the Priestly Office, which belongs not to them; and take the Cenſer into their hands, when Chriſt forbids them, Let them remember, that <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> periſhed by Fire; and <hi>Corah</hi> with his complices were ſwallowed up alive into the Earth, for committing ſuch things; and though their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences may be fair, and their deſigns honeſt; yet <hi>Uz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zah</hi> was ſmitten for his indiſcreet zeal, and died, though his intent was good: And if the word ſpoken by Angels was ſtedfaſt, and every trangreſſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a juſt recompence of reward, of how much ſorer puniſhment, ſuppoſe ye, ſhall they be thought worthy, who have troden under foot the Laws of Chriſt, and counted the blood of the Covenant an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy thing, and done deſpight to the Spirit of Graces.</p>
            <p>From the Subjects of the Apoſtles Diſcourſe, we proceed to conſider the Matter predicated of, or attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to them, which was the ſecond Particular deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the Words; and the other part of the Propoſition implicitely contained in them, <hi>They are the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103379:9"/>Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Myſteries of God;</hi> the proper intent and purpoſe whereof is really the ſame, to repreſent the juſt Authority of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Office; yet becauſe 'tis a complex Propoſition, the parts whereof are not in all reſpects coincident, and a reall difference is apparent in them, they may juſtly be ſevered in our conſideration of them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall be handled apart in our intended diſcourſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; the former reſpects the Authority and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Miniſters, <hi>They are the Miniſters of Chriſt:</hi> the latter their Office and employment: <hi>They are the Stewards of the Myſteries of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſider the Authority and Commiſſion of the Perſons in the Text: the Apoſtles and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors are the Miniſters of Chriſt: the former ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt in Perſon, or by an immediate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from Heaven, the latter regularly inveſted with ſame Commiſſion by the ſolemn Prayers of the Church, and Impoſition of hands by the principal Officers thereof; which was the Form of Ordination exerciſed by the Apoſtles themſelves, and other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in their Generations (as hath been already ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently demonſtrated) the practice whereof muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be a ſufficient Authority to Conſecrate others in the ſucceding ages of the Church, and all ſuch Perſons by virtue of that Apoſtolical Inſtitution re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly ordained according to the will of Chriſt, and without all controverſie acknowledged by him, as his Servants and Miniſters.</p>
            <p>For as Men and Angels were ſometimes employed by God, as Miniſters and Agents in the delivery of ſome Meſſage, as conveying ſome bleſſing to the World before the Incarnation of Chriſt; ſo our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord, that abſolute and ſupream Monarch of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103379:10"/>Church, in imitation of his Heavenly Father, call'd to his aſſiſtance a certain number of Perſons, to act the part of Miniſterial Officers under him the great Dioceſan, and Biſhop of mens Souls; and after his departure from the world, and Aſcenſion into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, poured down the Holy Ghoſt upon a full Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of them as they were Aſſembled to Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the worſhip of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. By whoſe deſcent they were immediately taught from God, inſpired infallibly to Preach the Goſpel, to confirm it by Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and had a gracious promiſe, that the ſame bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit ſhould attend them and their Succeſſors to the Worlds end; and accordingly when a compleat body of Religion was perfected, and the Scripture finiſhed, yea, ſo that that extraordinary work of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Revelation ceaſed; the Apoſtles in the name of Chriſt Ordained a degree of men to ſucceed them in Ordinary in that honourable Function of the Miniſtry, whoſe it is to Rule under Chriſt over the ſeveral Flocks,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and to ſpeak unto them the Word of God; which account we receive from St. <hi>Clemens</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> that as Chriſt was the Angel of God under the ſecond Covenant; ſo the Apoſtles were the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Chriſt, who being filled with the Holy Ghoſt, went forth and Preached the Kingdom of Heaven; and as the number of Converts increaſed, Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the moſt eminent and worthy Chriſtians to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Church, and perfect the body of Chriſt: from hence the Holy Ghoſt deſcribes theſe perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns by thoſe Phraſes and Expreſſions, which denote their relation to Chriſt to be like that of a Servant to a Maſter, or a Steward to a Lord; for ſo they are ſtyled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Meſſengers, that Receive Commiſſion from him to exerciſe Authority in his name over the Church;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103379:10"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Diſciples or followers of Chriſt as their Lord and Maſter; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Legates, or Ambaſſadours to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver ſome Meſſage from their Heavenly Soveraign to poor diſtreſſed mortals here on Earth; Parallel to which are thoſe other Appellations of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all which are uſed with reference to thoſe immediate Officers of Chriſt, who were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed as Commiſſioners under him, andſent with Authority from him, to treat with their fellow-Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the buſineſs of Religion, and to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Myſteries of the Goſpel to them; which by a juſt Analogy may alſo be attributed to all ſucceeding Miniſters, who are legally appointed to ſerve at the Altar of Chriſt, and to Miniſter to his People in Sacred things.</p>
            <p>Which is the ſecond part of the Propoſition, and reſpects the Office and employment of the Perſons ſpoken of in the Text, <hi>They are the Stewards of the Myſteries of God;</hi> that the Goſpel of Chriſt or the Doctrine of Chriſtianity is intended under this Phraſe, will moſt evidently appear, if we compare this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Apoſtle with others of the like Nature; and then conſider the moſt genuine import and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of them: in <hi>Col.</hi> 2.2. the Apoſtle profeſſing his ardent Zeal and Sollicitude for the Church of God at <hi>Coloſſi,</hi> and <hi>Laodicea,</hi> inſerteth this very expreſſion into his prayer for them, that they might be united with one accord, into the the knowledge and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Myſteries of God; of which he affirms in the next Verſe, That all Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge are contained in them, the ſame he calls their Faith in Chriſt, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. And receiving Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. Which Phraſes can admit of no other Expoſition to explicate their ſence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103379:11"/>and meaning, than to ſignifie the Chriſtian Doctrine, which at the firſt was delivered by the Lord, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards confirmed and perfected by them that heard him; Parallel to which is that Illuſtrious Aphoriſm of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. Great is the Myſtery of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; that is, the Religion of Chriſt, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the moſt excellent and perfect Rules of Piety; and that this notion requires ſo general a ſignification appears, by the ſeveral branches enumerated by the Apoſtle, as a Baſis or Foundation to ſupport the Church of God, which were the common received Articles of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>For that men might not wander eternall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the dark, and an everlaſting blindneſs poſſeſs their Souls; it hath pleaſed the infinitely Wiſe and Gracious God to communicate to the World, by Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion many ſublime and myſterious points, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe is neceſſary to be believed and obſerved in order to Mens Salvation; and that theſe things might be perpetuated to the World, and ſecured from the corruptions or invaſions of Enemies, it ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt to commit them to writing in the Sacred Records of Holy Scripture; which by an eſpeciall providence are preſerved entire to this very day in the Canonical Books of the Old and New Teſtament; which latter was the only Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion laid by the Apoſtles; and therefore the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Books contained therein, the ſum and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Chriſtian Faith, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, was made manifeſt and known to the Saints; and ſo certainly could not remain in unwritten Traditions; for then it would have been hid from the World, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.26. And another Apoſtle calls it the Faith, once, or at once delivered, <hi>Jude</hi> 3. Which directly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103379:11"/>oppoſeth any Innovation or Introduction of Doctrines into the Goſpel after its conſummation by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; which is an aſſertion of ſuch Catholick verity, that all the Writers in the Church of Chriſt have conſtantly acknowledged it, till thoſe few perſons in the late Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> durſt venture to reject the univerſal Tradition of the Church, and run coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with the beſt Antiquity; which is plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated by the incomparable induſtry, and ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate inquiry of the late Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> in his Scholaſtical Hiſtory of the Canon of Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>So that, though the Writings of Apocryphical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors may be Read in the Church of God, for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of life, and inſtruction of manners; yet, the Governours of our Church in Compiling her pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Liturgy, have appointed no part of thoſe Books to be Read, but what is agreeable to Canonical Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and always accounted their Authority too weak to lay any Foundation for, or to eſtabliſh any neceſſary Doctrine upon: Which was the Judgment of Saint <hi>Jerome,</hi> concerning this matter, who was alſo the moſt ſtrenuous Aſſertor of the certain and indubitate Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of Holy Writers; for, ſpeaking of the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Apocrypha, he ſaith, <hi>Legit quidem Eccleſia, ſed eas inter Canonicas non recipit,</hi> and though we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Name and Number of Canonical Books from the Authority of humane Tradition, and upon the ſame credit believe thoſe Copies which now we enjoy, to be Authentick, and in all material parts agreeable to the moſt Primitive Writings of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles; yet we dare not receive the Traditions of men, as the Doctrine of God; nay, we utterly reject ſuch Impoſitions, as preſumptuous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103379:12"/>and impudent, and are afraid of the Curſe of God, if we ſhould receive them as Articles of Faith; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Holy Ghoſt in the Comſummation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, hath conſign'd and Sealed it up with an <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema, Rev.</hi> 22.18, 19. <hi>Iteſtifie,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore the Church of <hi>England</hi> according to the practice of the Catholick Church in all Ages, ſince the time of the Apoſtles, hath preſcribed the ſame Canon of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and utterly diſclaimed all pretence of Adition to, or Detraction from it, as 'tis recited in the Sixth Article of our Religion. So that the written Word of God, the Sacred Records of the Goſpel, the ſeveral Contents therein, the various parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and no other Writings or Traditions, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever are that <hi>depoſitum</hi> committed to the charge of all Miniſterial Officers, whoſe duty it is to preſerve and improve the ſame according to the pleaſure of their Lord and Maſter; for this purpoſe they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Stewards of God, and Diſpenſers of Holy My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms in general, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18, 19, 20. <hi>God hath given Us the Miniſtry of Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and committed to Us the Word of Peace, that we are Ambaſſadours for Chriſt, to pray men in Chriſts ſtead to be reconciled unto God;</hi> and in particular, proclaims of himſelf, that he was appointed a Preacher of the Goſpel, and an Apoſtle, and a Teacher of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11. And for this reaſon he exhorts <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> to ſtir up the gift of God which was in him, by the putting on of his hands, to hold faſt the form of ſound words, which he had heard of him, and to keep by the Holy Ghoſt, the good thing which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6, 13, 14. To which agrees that deſcription of a Miniſter or Preſident in Sacred affairs delivered by that Myſtical Divine, that he is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103379:12"/>the proper Interpreter of Divine Theology,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the Angel of Almighty God, being to learn from thoſe Divinely inſpired Oracles, and then to teach and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain them to the Church.</p>
            <p>And if the Commiſſion of thoſe Apoſtolical Perſons be reſtrained within the preſcription of certain bounds, that they durſt not go beyond the command of the Lord, to do either good or bad of their own mind, had power to ſay nothing in the name of Chriſt, but what he communicated to them by Divine Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and none to diminiſh ought of what he bid them ſpeak, (for though they enjoyed under Chriſt the greateſt preheminence imaginable in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affairs; yet they durſt not detract from, or add to the will of God, by Preaching up their own fancies, and the imaginations of their own Brains; this St. <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth of himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1. <hi>to</hi> 7. And both the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles do ſeriouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, that whatever they delivered to the World (as to all the main and neceſſary parts of Doctrine) they received it from Chriſt in Perſon, or by Revelation from the Holy Ghoſt; as we may well believe, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thoſe miraculous gifts and graces, which were communicated to them; which was an irrefragable demonſtration of the Spirit and Power of God, by which they ſpake;) 'tis highly abſurd to imagine that their Succeſſors ſhould have greater liberty in the Church of Chriſt, and eſpecially at ſuch a vaſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time from the propagation of the Goſpel and the ceſſation of Miracles; indeed it might be deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly accounted a Miracle, not the leaſt, if we ſhould be Soveraign Lords over mens Conſciences, or have abſolute dominion in matters of Faith, if our Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſhould be of an unlimited Nature, like the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103379:13"/>which <hi>Tiberius</hi> gave <hi>Druſus</hi> upon a certain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, <hi>Nullis certis mandatis, exre conſulturum;</hi> that every man might have the power of a Plenipotentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and deliver what ſeems good in his own eyes; when every tittle of our Errand is comprized by God, rati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and confirmed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om Heaven, and explicitely contained in the grand Charter of our Commiſſion; the Records of the Goſpel: So that as the Civil Law adjudgeth thoſe Ambaſſadors guilty of High Treaſon, who tranſcend the bounds and limits of their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and both Modern and Ancient Hiſtories Record, that ſuch preſumption hath received a juſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward; the Apoſtles always accounted it a Sacrilege moſt horrid and inexcuſable in the ſight of their Maſter, and loaded that Perſon with a moſt dreadful <hi>Anathema,</hi> who ſhould preſume to broach his own Inventions, and to intermingle them with the Doctrine of the Goſpel, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8 9. If we, or an Angel from Heaven Preach any other Doctrine, then that ye have already received, let him be accurſed; which Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ical Conſtitution is of equal Authority in the Church, to this very day; for in reference to that Text, is that gloſs of St. <hi>Auſtin. Maledictus eſt qui quidpiam praedicat, praeterquam, quod in Scripturis Legis and Evangelii recepimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if theſe things be true, what juſt indignation may the Maſter of our Religion conceive againſt the preſumption and boldneſs of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which advanceth the Pope into His Tribunal, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes a like power, might and dominion to him, as to the eternal Son of God! For though Chriſt alone can inſtruct us in the Laws and Ordinances of his Kingdom, and by the influence of his Spirit direct us in the way of life; though that pretended Vicar of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103379:13"/>Chriſt be ſtyled the Miniſter of our Lord, and in his Canons and Decrees ſubſcribe himſelf; <hi>Epiſcopus &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus Servorum Dei;</hi> yet dares he proudly uſurp the moſt proper Offices of his Maſter, and boldly aſſume the Title of Head of the Church: For he, as they confidently boaſt, hath received full Authority from Chriſt to deliver the whole will of God to the World; and to decide all Controverſies in Religion, who, according to them, is certainly infallible, when he acts as Head of the Church, whom the Holy Ghoſt doth continually attend in Council, lawfully Summon'd, and in his Conſiſtory aſſiſts him to Judge infallibly of Spiritual affairs; he hath Supremacy over the Souls of Men, can diſpenſe with Divine Laws, diſſolve mens Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of obedience to them, and ſecure their Perſons from the wrath of God, which for their diſobedience they juſtly deſerve; he can conſtitute new Articles of Faith, and impoſe his definitions on the whole World, as Credentials neceſſary to mans Salvation; the Keys of Heaven are delivered to him, for though Chritſt alone opens and no man ſhuts, and ſhuts and no man opens, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.7. Yet, by Succeſſion to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> he dares Sit and Reign as Univerſal Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, by his Papal Authority determining the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Life and Death; and according to mens ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of them, adjudging them to the one or other: as if he that Reigns in Heaven above, and Rules on Earth beneath, had ceaſed to execute his Kingly Office over the Church, and had derived it to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Succeſſor, and to the Pope as Univerſal Vicar.</p>
            <p>That theſe are indeed the Principles of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and not the ſlanderous ſuggeſtion of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, is apparently manifeſt, not only from the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of their private Doctors, but from the decretals
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103379:14"/>of their general Councils, and the moſt ſolemn Bulls of ſeveral Popes; in which they have acted ſo directly oppoſite to the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Goſpel, that they have exerciſed Authority over Chriſt himſelf, and by their Traditions made the Goſpel of Chriſt of no effect: Witneſs that Decree concerning the Canon of Scripture, in the Fourth Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> Celebrated under <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, wherein it was declared, that the Books of Apocrypha, and all their unwritten Traditions, are equally the Dictates of Gods Spirit with the moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Scripture,<note place="margin">Synodus Libros Scriptos, &amp; ſine ſc. tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam velore tenus a Chriſto, vel a Spiritu Sancto dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas pari Pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis affectu ac reverentiâ ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit ac vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur. Si quis autem ſciens &amp; prudens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempſcrit, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema ſit.</note> and as neceſſary to confirm any Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith, and to preſcribe Rules for the regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of manners; and therefore to be embraced with the like affection of Piety, and received with the ſame religious Reverence, under peril of the moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Anathema.</hi> And now I appeal to the judgment of and ſober conſiderate man, whether ſuch Doctrines as theſe are agreeable to the Tenor of the Goſpel, and becoming the Miniſters of Chriſt, or not rather highly derogatory to the dignity and honour of his Majeſty, as being palpably erroneous, and horridly blaſphemous; if tried by the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament, which are the only Canon of Faith and good manners.</p>
            <p>We have hitherto conſidered the Doctrine of the Text; which was naturally contained in the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Particulars; that the Apoſtles and all other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons lawfully Conſecrated into their Spiritual Office, <hi>are the Miniſters of Chriſt, and the Stewards of the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of God.</hi> Now both the Nature of the precedeing Diſcourſe, and the Order of the Method propounded, require our conſideration concerning the laſt Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; which contains Two practical Inferences dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103379:14"/>from the truth of the Apoſtles Aſſertion: One re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the men to whom theſe Perſons are employed as Miniſters and Stewards: <hi>Let a man ſo account of Us,—</hi> The, other relating to the Perſons themſelves, to whom this Office is committed: <hi>Moreover 'tis requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Stewards, that a man be found faithful;</hi> both which are a compleat and neceſſary Application to our preſent diſcourſe, and require our moſt ſerious conſideration.</p>
            <p>Firſt concerning the men to whom theſe Perſons are employed <hi>as Miniſters and Stewards;</hi> the Apoſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers this exhortation, <hi>Let a man ſo account of Us;</hi> which words will eaſily admit of a double Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thereby preſent the Laity with a Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold duty concerning their reſpect and carriage to the Clergy.
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, That they ſet no greater value upon them.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, That they account ſo worthily of them, <hi>as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Goſpel.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, That men ſet no greater value upon the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, than what their Office and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment requires: <hi>They are the Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> not Miniſters of their Peoples Conſciences: <hi>They are the Stewards of God,</hi> not Lords over any mens Faith; 'tis therefore unreaſonable for men to terminate their glory in the worth and excellency of thoſe that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe the Myſteries of Salvation; and a pride, not much inferior to that of <hi>Herod,</hi> for theſe to take ſuch honour to themſelves: It was this Oſtentation in the People, and this Ambition among ſome of the Clergy, that occaſioned thoſe Schiſms and Diviſions in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> when the Chriſtian Converts in the Regions of <hi>Achaia</hi> adhered ſo implicitely to the Authority of thoſe Miniſters from whom they received the Faith, that they ſlighted and diſregarded the Preaching of others; whilſt they magnified the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103379:15"/>of their own Apoſtles, as men ſhould adore the Oracles of God: For this reaſon I conceive the Apoſtle ſo ſharply reproves their erroneous conceit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 13, 14. <hi>Was</hi> Paul <hi>crucified for you? Or were you Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in the name of</hi> Paul? <hi>I thank God, I Baptized none of you, that men might not glory in my name:</hi> Or elſe becauſe of thoſe gifts and excellencies, which they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended more eminent in one Apoſtle than in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, every one as his Fancy directed, admiring ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> or <hi>Cephas.</hi> One extolling the powerfull plainneſs of <hi>Paul,</hi> whoſe diſcourſe was ſharp as a two-edged Sword, and his arguments ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and weighty, the weapons of whoſe warfare were not carnal, but mighty to the pulling down of ſtrong holds. Another applauding the fulneſs of <hi>Apollos,</hi> as one that could entertain their minds with an ample variety of Heavenly Rhetorick, could expatiate upon the glory of Heaven, as if he ſaw the Gates of that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> open and Chriſt Jeſus ſitting at the right hand of God, and inlarge upon the torments of Hell, as if he heard the languiſhing cryes, and ſaw the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable miſeries of the Damned. A third admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſolidity and perſpicuity of <hi>Cephas,</hi> who could explain the Oracles of God, and unriddle the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Salvation to the life; the depth of Divinity he was able to fathom, and to render the moſt difficult points plain and intelligible; ſo much had the Spirit of Antichriſt poſſeſt the Spirit of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that they forgat the Lord their Redeemer, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to glory in men, whilſt they neglected to render unto God the honour of their gifts and graces, and attributed it to the induſtry and endeavour of his Servants and his Stewards and Vaſſals, as if thoſe who were at beſt but the Miniſters of Chriſt and Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103379:15"/>of God had been the ſole Authors of their faith, and could infallibly finiſh their Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But the Apoſtle ſo extremely diſliked the weakneſs and vanity of thoſe Perſons, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their ſplendid profeſſion of the Chriſtian faith, and glorious oſtentation in their reſpective Miniſters, he confidently tells them they were ſo far from being Spiritually eminent in the Church, that they were but carnal men, and nothing Superior to the moſt imperfect Chriſtians, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4. After which reprehenſion he ſubjoyns a moſt ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Admonition to inſtruct the <hi>Corinthians</hi> and all Chriſtian profeſſors, with that juſt meaſure of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reſpect, which the Miniſters of Chriſt ſhould be entertained withall; that they are Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, and Miniſters attending in the Church for mens Salvation; but their abilities are neither the endowments of Nature, nor the meer advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Education and induſtry; but all their ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency is of God, who diſtributes to every man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the pleaſure of his own will, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the glory of mens Converſion to the Faith, of their Edification in it, and Salvation by reaſon of it; ſhould be attributed to God as the Principal efficient cauſe, who both preventeth his Miniſters in all their undertakings, and bleſſeth their labours with good ſucceſs; which is the ſubſtance of the Apoſtles ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5, 6, 7. And is excellently illuſtrated by the Paraphraſe of the Learned Doctor <hi>Hammond,</hi> and the Marginal Annotations of <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Treme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius.</hi> Yet as if the Writing of the Apoſtles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned not us, and the Church of Chriſt were in no great danger by the fond dotages and vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Oſtentation of Schiſmatical and Carnal Spirits;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103379:16"/>with what confidence and vigour have the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> been frequently renewed and reinforc'd upon the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, as if they were entailed to the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and were inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Companions to the Goſpel of Chriſt? For alas! moſt wofull experience too plainly manifeſts, that thoſe who call upon the Name of Chriſt, and lay the greateſt claim to an intereſt in him, moſt wickedly arrogate that glory which is due to His Majeſty, to thoſe inſtruments who are men of like paſſions and infirmities with themſelves: For how common is it for Chriſtians to ſeparate, and ſtand at a more than ordinary diſtance from their fellow-Chriſtians; and when they have adopted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into this or that Party, to cry up their Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the only true Religion, to confine the Spirit of God within the Walls they Aſſemble; and to look with reproach, contempt and ſcorn upon thoſe that will not be as Schiſmatical in the Church and diſobedient to Governours as themſelves? So wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly do men abuſe their own Conſciences with the Vizor of an Hypocrital Zeal, and under the pretence of a ſingular Piety diſhonour the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, when they adhere to their Teachers more than Chriſt, adoring their Perſons, though never ſo Ignorant and unlearned, as if an Angel from Heaven were dropt down among them, like the Image of <hi>Diana,</hi> among the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitely aſſenting to whatever they deliver, though never ſo ridiculous and abſurd; as if the gods were come down to them in the likeneſs of men, or at leaſt they ſpake the very Oracles of God; of theſe men the Apoſtles long ſince Propheſied, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4. <hi>After their own luſts, ſhall men heap to themſelves
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103379:16"/>Teachers, having itching Ears, who ſhall turn away their Ears from the Truth, and be turned unto Fables:</hi> But my Brethren theſe things ought not ſo to be, there is one only Lawgiver, Jeſus Chriſt the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and who art thou that conſtituteſt another? 'Tis an excellent ſaying of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> and extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pertinent to our preſent judgment;<note place="margin">Orat. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> I reverence <hi>Peter,</hi> yet will not I be called a <hi>Petrian:</hi> I honour <hi>Paul,</hi> yet will not I be called a <hi>Paulian:</hi> But the Aſſertion of <hi>Lactantius,</hi> though very ſevere,<note place="margin">Inſtit. L.<hi>4.</hi> C. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly true, <hi>Chriſtiani eſſe deſièrunt, qui Chriſti no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine amiſſo, humana and externa vocabula induerunt:</hi> And indeed 'tis ſuch a reproach to Chriſtianity, for its Profeſſors to aſſume thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">De Conſc, Prael, P. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> that as the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> ſadly complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Non eſt dignus, qui ſit Chriſti, qui non eſt Unius Chriſti diſcipulus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if men did ſeriouſly deſign the Peace of their own Conſciences, or the proſperity of the Church and State in which they live, they would rejoyce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly in the Name of Chriſtians alone, would reverently obſerve the lawfull Conſtitutions of a well ſettled National Church, and embrace Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in its purity and ſimplicity, without any ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter reſpect to Parties and Diviſions. I heartily wiſh that the Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> do neither by their flattery or puſillanimity, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance or lukewarmneſs contribute any thing to theſe ſad diſtractions in this Nation; and I humbly beg that they will moſt ſeriouſly declaim againſt, and ſincerely endeavour to ſuppreſs ſuch extravagant vanities in the Religion of their Auditors, and that the People of this Kingdom would once be perſuad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into this neceſſary piece of Chriſtian Prudence,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103379:17"/>not to think of their Teachers more than they ought, but whatever Reverence they bear to their Perſons, however fair and plauſible their reaſonings may ſeem to their weak underſtandings, to let none of their Stratagems deceive their Souls, nor a Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Words to ſway their Judgments to make unjuſt ſeparations in the body of Chriſts Church, to affront the Authority of the lawful Powers, by which under God they are protected; much leſs to be perverted from any one Article in the Chriſtian Faith, or to receive any Doctrine that overthrows it; for this is the Command of him, who is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Potentate, and Lord over Heaven and Earth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.6, 7, 9. <hi>Though your Patriots love the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Rooms at Feaſts, and the chief ſeats in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and to be called of men, Rabbi, Rabbi; yet call no man your Father upon the Earth, for one is your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Exhortation of the Apoſtles admits of this Expoſition, that men account ſo worthily of theſe Perſons, <hi>As the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of God;</hi> as thoſe denominations, are applied to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters which denote their ſervitude and ſubjection to Chriſt, ſo the ſame and other Titles of honour are attributed to them; which import ſome Power and Authority inherent in them; thus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> denotes their Dignity and Commiſſion in the Government of the Church; for as in Temporal Kingdoms, when Rulers or Procurators are ſent into any Province, they receive Authority to regulate the affairs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as Deputies or Vicegerents to their Soveraign Lord; ſo Chriſt ſent forth his Apoſtles with Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Succeed him in the Adminiſtration of the Government of his Spiritual Kingdom, to execu <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:103379:17"/>in his Name ſeveral Offices in the Church, which he in Perſon performed when he was converſant with it, thereof they are called by the Holy Ghoſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. Of like ſignification is that honourable Appellation of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which reſpects the eminent Dignity of the Miniſterial Officers, who are employed by the Prince of Heaven, as his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors to Treat and Negotiate with the Sons of of Men, concerning the Myſterious affairs of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Kingdom: For ſo the <hi>Romans</hi> gave the Title of Legates to thoſe Perſons, who were inveſted with Dignity to repreſent their Maſters Perſon, and with Authority to manage their Commiſſion with Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign States; which employment as it highly advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the Dignity of theſe Officers, ſo it juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires from men an honourable reſpect to their Meſſage, and a Reverend eſtimation of their Perſons; and for this St. <hi>Paul</hi> commends his beloved <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> becauſe of their kindneſs and obedience to <hi>Titus,</hi> that out of reſpect to his Spiritual Function, with fear and trembling they had received him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.15. In conformity to which practice, the Apoſtle frequently inſerts an Exhortation of the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as a neceſſary injunction to the Church, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12, 13. We beſeech you Brethren to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and to eſteem them very highly in love for their works ſake; and <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your Souls, as they that muſt give account: and from hence St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> to Unity and Order,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:103379:18"/>preſents them with that repect,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Epiſt. ad Smyrn. <hi>p. 6.</hi>
               </note> which is due to the Officers of the Church, as a proper expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent thereto. Let the Biſhop be obeyed as your Spiritual Father; the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> as the Apoſtles of Chriſt; and the Deacons rever'd in obedience to the Command of God; let nothing be done without the Biſhops appointment.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs that the beſt of us are but men of like Paſſions and infirmities with others, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently many imperfections through the degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy of humane Nature are in us unavoidable, and perhaps there may be ſome in ſacred Orders very diſorderly in their lives and profane in their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; ſuch as ſhould adorn the ſoundneſs of their Doctrines by the holineſs of their Converſations, but bring it into contempt and deriſion by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy and vitious courſe; yet ſo long as their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are ſound and Orthodox, and till they are ſuſpended from their Office by lawfull Authority, (which is heartily to be wiſht) they ſtand in Chriſts ſtead, who hath extended his Precept concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this very purpoſe to the vileſt of men, that People ſhould follow the good Doctrine of their Teachers, not the evil example of their Lives and Actions, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.2, 3. So that though the Perſon for his immoralities deſerve to be degraded into the loweſt Rank of Chriſtians, according to the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Fifth of the Apoſtles Canons, and upon continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diſobedience after ſufficient admonition, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled the Chriſtian Church, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. Yet 'tis eaſie to diſtinguiſh his Office and Employment from his perſonal vices, and neceſſary to reſpect him for his Works ſake.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:103379:18"/>
            <p>But I may return from this digreſſion, and take up a juſt reprehenſion againſt an impudent Generation of Men, who are not afraid to abuſe the Meſſengers of Chriſt, and to confront the Meſſage delivered by them; ſuch as deride and affront their Perſons, as if they were the refuſe and off-ſcouring of the World, and indeavour by Sacrilege and injuſtice to deprive them of their competent and neceſſary Allowance, which the Laws of God have commanded in general, and the contribution of charitable friends with the juſt Authority of the civil Powers have preſcribed in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; moſt contrary to the Canon of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.18. <hi>That thoſe who labour in the Word and Doctrine, be counted worthy of double honour, for the labourer is worthy of his reward:</hi> And an Ordinance of Chriſt himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. <hi>That they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> Such as refuſe to attend to his Ambaſſage though of Divine Authority, and neglect to conſider the grand importance of it, though he ſpeak the very Oracles of God, and diſcourſe to them of the Kingdom of Heaven: Such as ſcorn to endure the reproof of their Miniſter, though never ſo juſt and neceſſary, and are inraged at his reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though uſhered with meekneſs, wiſdom, and gravity; whoſe affections are ſo corrupt, and their Spirits ſo haughty, that they become his enemies, becauſe he tells them the Truth, and if the Power of their hand were equal to the Paſſion of their hearts, would Parallel the Oppreſſion of <hi>Ahab,</hi> the Impiety of <hi>Jehoiakim,</hi> or the Cruelty of <hi>Herod; Et alia inſunt ſtolida &amp; vana, vel ſi molliùs acciperes miſeranda, ſed non ad invidiam iſta, verum conciliandae miſericordiae refero:</hi> Which <hi>Epiphonema</hi> of the Hiſtorian, may be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:103379:19"/>by the words of the Apoſtle in the Language of the Holy Ghoſt; we are made a Spectacle unto the World, to Angels, and to men, we are fools for Chriſts ſake, being deſpiſed and reviled, I ſpeak not theſe things to ſhame our enemies, but as a faithful Miniſter of Chriſt to warn and remember them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Father forgive them, they know not what they do, they conſider not what reproach and affront, they caſt upon thy Son our Maſter, when they contemn and diſhonour us his immediate Servants; which yet our Lord hath expreſly ſignified, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16. <hi>He that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me, and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me.</hi> But that we may be perſwaded better things of the People in our ſeveral charges, may this Petition be inſerted into our daily Litany, that they will cheerfully aſcend to the Houſe of God, to recieve inſtruction; will attend with reverence and devotion to our Words of Exhortation, will impartially examine and ſeriouſly conſider the rational importance of our Doctrines and Admonitions, and either friendlily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us, if any Error or Corruption fall from us; or if we ſpeak the truth in Chriſt, and lie not, faithfully believe, and ſincerely obey us. But whether Men will hear, or whether they will forbear, let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Vocation, whereto we are called, that arming our ſelves with the reſolution of St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 20.24.</note> 
               <hi>That ther Bonds nor afflictions ſhall move us: neither will we count our life dear unto us, ſo that we may finiſh our Courſe with joy, and the Miniſtry we have received of the Lord Jeſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> We may attain the Chriſtian ſimplicity and courage of that bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>And approve our ſelves the faithful Miniſters of Chriſt, and good Stewards of the Myſteries of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:103379:19"/>
            <p>Which is the Second Inference delivered in the Text, and reſpects the Perſons, who are the Miniſters and Stewards of the Goſpel, that they be faithfull in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their Office commited to them: <hi>Moreover 'tis required in Stewards, that a man be found faithfull;</hi> the juſt deſign of which Exhortation will be fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by them, if they be endowed with theſe two qualifications.
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, A good underſtanding of their Office and Employment.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, A good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the diſcharge and performance of it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, A good underſtanding of their Office and Employment, <hi>is neceſſary in the Stewards of God, that they be found faithfull;</hi> for 'tis impoſſible that men be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their Stewardſhip, whoſe intellectuals are Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally defective, or their underſtanding, though capable of improvement, yet rude and ignorant in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their duty. How can they diſcharge the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Teachers, that have need to be taught the firſt Principles of the Oracles of God? Or how can thoſe Perſons inſtruct their People in the Myſteries of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that are Novices in the Faith of Chriſt, and know not thoſe Canons by which the Houſe of God is to be ruled? and how ſhall they then take care of the Church to preſerve it pure and undefiled, or be able by ſo und Doctrine to exhort and convince the gainſayer? 'Tis our Saviours obſervation, if the blind lead the blind, they ſhall both fall into the Ditch: So ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary 'tis that the Miniſters of Religion be themſelves ſufficiently inſtructed, that they may communicate to others in all Spiritual knowledge: And as the <hi>Lacedae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians</hi> called the Governours of their City, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe they framed the diſpoſitions, and faſhioned the manners of their Subjects according to the Laws of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:103379:20"/>their repective Communities; and the Wiſe <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> for the ſame reaſon gave their Rulers the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, and ſtyled them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe they conſtituted good and wholeſom Laws for the direction of the People, and uſed moſt prevalent means to have them obſerved. So God that Soveraign Lord of his People hath given the like Appellations to the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in his Church, the Miniſters of Spiritual affairs, as Seers, Prophets, Overſeers and Stewards, that from the ſignification of their Name, they may be put in remembrance of their duty, that the Preiſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge, and the People ſhould ſeek the Law at their mouths.</p>
            <p>What the Office of a Miniſter in general is, hath been already diſcourſed, when we conſidered that <hi>depoſitum</hi> committed to his charge, and for whole ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice it ſhould be employed, the ſubſtance of which is, that the whole will of God concerning mans Salvation be faithfully delivered and explain'd, as 'tis contained in the Goſpel of Chriſt; the particular Offices, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this general duty is to be performed are briefly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in thoſe ſhort inſtructions recommended to the Miniſters of Chriſt in their Ordinations; to them are committed the bleſſed Sacraments of the Chriſtian Religion; that as opportunity ſerves, and neceſſity requireth, they Adminiſter thoſe Sacred Rites in the Church of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24, 25.</note> by Baptizing ſuch as are duly diſpoſed for that Solemn Ordinance and diſtributing the Holy Communion to thoſe pious and humble Souls that are Religiouſly diſpoſed to celebrate the honour of God in that Sacred Inſtitution; and into their hands me S. Sc: are put, who are Commanded to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnize the worſhip of God is publick, either as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:103379:20"/>Prieſts to wait at the Altar of Lord, to intercede with his Majeſty in the behalf of the People, and to preſent in their ſtead, Prayers, and ſupplications and thanksgivings to him; this St. <hi>Paul</hi> gave in charge to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2. And for this reaſon that great Apoſtle ſo frequently inſerts his Petitions in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to his beloved Converts, proteſting that he ſhould ſin againſt God, if he neglected to pray for them, and reſolving never to omit ſo neceſſary a duty; and upon this accout thoſe publick Offices were compoſed in the Primitive Church, and Hours of Prayer appointed that the Prieſts might almoſt continually be praying for the People; according to which practice 'tis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by our Church, that the Miniſters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on offer up a Morning and Evening Sacrifice to the Throne of Grace, in the publick Service and Liturgy of our Church, which in all Cathedral Churches, and Collegiate Chapels is duly obſerved; or as Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors to treat with the People in the buſineſs of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reveal the Will of their Maker to them, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully explaining the Goſpel in its true and prosper ſence, and framing their diſcourſes according to the qualities and capacities of their Auditors, that their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings may be well informed in the Principles of Religion, and their hearts ſtrongly confirmed in the Faith; to warn ſinners of the evil of their ways, and to Preach up the duties of a Practical Religion, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them with the moſt convincing Reaſons and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull Exhortations to a good Life, if by any means, the hearts of men may be inclined to the love, and their lives to the practice of as univerſal Piety. Hitherto may be referred that neceſſary Office of Catechizing the Chriſtian youth by ſome ſhort and familiar Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:103379:21"/>concerning the Eſſential parts of Religion, which if duly performed by the Miniſters of Religion, would in a great meaſure prevent that infidelity and profaneneſs, ſo ſcandalous and offenſive in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church, even by thoſe which are arrived to the uſe of Reaſon, and the exerciſe of their underſtanding: For this purpoſe, that admirable <hi>Compendium</hi> of the Chriſtian Religion, the Catechiſm of our Church is commanded to be learned by every Baptized Perſon, before he be confirmed by the Biſhop, that he may be able to give an account of his Faith, before he be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Holy Communion.</p>
            <p>But the duty of a Miniſter is ſtill of larger extent. The Apoſtle tells us, and experience too truly manifeſts what buſie Agents the Emiſſaries of Satan are to diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate the Doctrine of Devils, and to ſpread abroad moſt damnable Errors; of which ſort are they that creep into private Houſes, and lead Captive ſilly Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, laden with divers luſts, and thoſe falſe Teachers, who being unruly and vain Talkers and Deceivers, call in Queſtion the moſt undeniable Principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and turn the grace of God into laſciviouſneſs, whoſe folly ſhould be made manifeſt to all men, and their mouths ſtopt, that they proceed no further; which is certainly the duty of thoſe men, to whom the word of God is committed, that they may be able by ſound Doctrine to convince and reclaim the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayer, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5, 9. For 'tis abſurd to conceive, that the care and vigilance of Miniſters whoſe employment is to watch over Souls, and to endeavour their Salvation, may without affront to their Lord and Maſter be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the pains and ſolicitude of thoſe Seducers, whoſe buſineſs is to tempt and intice men to ſin, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:103379:21"/>thereby to aſcertain their eternal Damnation. So that 'tis undoubtedly their Office by Private inſtruction and admonition as well as by Publick, to contend earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the Faith of Chriſt, againſt the clamorous and impertinent cavils of malicious Spirits and falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels; to ſtudy the preſervation of the Truth in the hearts of thoſe unhappy Perſons that are aſſaulted by them, that they neither embrace the Errors of thoſe men, nor fall into a ſtate of ſin and Death; and to wreſtle with God by their moſt fervent and importunate prayers, till their People are delivered from the ſnares of the Devil, and their Souls confirmed in the way of life; thus St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he had called together the Elders at <hi>Miletus,</hi> committed to them, the Flock of God, and warned them of falſe Teachers, that they faithfully watch againſt their Invaſions, leaſt they draw away Diſciples after them, <hi>Acts.</hi> 20.28, 29, 30, 31.</p>
            <p>Add to all this, the groſs Ignorance of many, which cryes aloud for Perſonal inſtruction; the open Prophaneſs of others, which ſtands in need of the moſt ſerious Admonitions, and ſeaſonable Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from their Spiritual Guides; and always the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation of the Sick is incumbent on them, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thier various conditions require the moſt affectionate Exhortations and convincing Arguments to confirm their Patience, to increaſe their Faith, to quicken thier Hope, to compleat their Repentance, and to perfect their Charity: All which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hath Ordained as a perpetual Office in the Church, <hi>James</hi> 5.14. <hi>Is any man ſick among you? let him call for the Elders of the Church, and let them pray over him, and the prayer of Faith ſhall ſave the ſick.</hi> All which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:103379:22"/>particulars are briefly recommended to the Care and endeavour of <hi>Polycarp</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> by <hi>Ignatius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and comprehended in the Epiſtle of <hi>Polycarp</hi> to the <hi>Presbyters</hi> of <hi>Philippi,</hi> as their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and indiſpenſable Offices: Theſe are the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts of the Miniſters Office, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neceſſary to be known by the Stewards of God, that by theſe Spiritual Miniſtries, they may faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſcarge their duty in the Family and Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed to the Second branch of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Exhortation to the Miniſters of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> A good Conſcience in the diſcharge and performance of their Office. And if the Solemnity of our Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or the Injunction of our Lord and Maſter; if the manifold Advantages which our faithfulneſs will infallibly effect, or the ſevere Account we muſt render to God concerning our Stewardſhip; if any or all of theſe have any weight and importance in them, they lay the ſtricteſt Obligation upon us, to engage our faithfulneſs in the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. For in our Ordination we received Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to preach the Goſpel, and explain the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to Adminiſter the Sacraments and other Rites and Ceremonies belonging to the Church; and when we received Inſtitution from our Dioceſan, were ſtrictly enjoyned to watch over the Flock of Chriſt, of which we were oppointed Overſeers; and if the Goſpel of our bleſſed Saviour be of Divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, what variety of Precepts are then delivered by God himſelf? There being neither an Evangeliſt, nor an Apoſtle, but from the Spirit of the Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes our Duty, and requires our Fidelity: Beſides,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:103379:22"/>the Glory of God is extremely concerned; the Salvation of our People lyes at Stake, and our own everlaſting Doom moſt certainly depends upon the faithful Diſcharge or wretched Neglect of our Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Employment. For by the ſtrength of this Argument St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts <hi>Timothy,</hi> to diſcharge his duty, with the greateſt care and a good Conſcience. I charge thee before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt who ſhall judge the quick and the dead, at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing and his Kingdom, that thou obſerve theſe things, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.</p>
            <p>But becauſe he that is unjuſt in his own affairs will ſcarce be faithfull in Adminiſtring the goods of others; I mean if our Conſciences be looſe and treacherous in ordering our own lives, we ſhall diſcover but little Conſcience in preſcribing Rules and Directions to others; or if we do employ our knowledge and our ſtrength to explain the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Salvation to the Souls committed to our charge, we cannot challenge a Bleſſing from God upon our endeavours, nor rationally expect that our labours ſhould be ſucceſsful; for God himſelf hath taken up a quarrel againſt ſuch men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16, 17—<hi>Unto the wicked ſaith God, What haſt thou to do, to declare my Statutes, or to take my Covenant in thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and caſteſt my words behind thee? therefore I will reprove thee, and ſet thy ſins in order before thy eyes.</hi> And the Apoſtle aſſures us that ſuch men are inexcuſable before God, and that his Sacred Name is blaſphemed by them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1, 17---24. And as our People may juſtly upbraid the Indecency and abſurdity of our Lives, when our Actions confront our Doctrines, and our
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:103379:23"/>Manners give our Preaching the Lye, as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> hath obſerved, <hi>Perdit Authoritatem docendi, cujus Sermo ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re deſtruitur;</hi> ſo they may be provoked to reproach and contemn the Goſpel it ſelf, as an unholy Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, or a fabulous Legend; like thoſe in <hi>Salvian</hi>'s time, <hi>Si Chriſtus Sancta docuiſſet, Chriſtiani Sanctè vixiſſent.</hi> Of what great concernment is it then, that we demonſtrate our knowledge in the ſound Myſteries of Religion, by our Reverent apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them, and a Religious deportment in the whole courſe and frame of our actions, correſpondent to them? That every Article of the Chriſtian Faith, of whoſe truth we labour to perſuade our People, be influential upon our Practices in ſuch proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24, 25.</note> that if there come in one that believeth not, or one that is unlearned, into our Aſſemblies; he may be convinced, and falling down on his face worſhip God, and report that God is in us of a truth: And every Precept in the Body of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, which we binde upon the Conſciences of men, and exhort them to practice, may be delineated ſo fairly in our Lives and Converſations, that <hi>others ſeeing our good works may glorifie our Father which is in Heaven.</hi> Such was the faithfulneſs of our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in this particular, that without any remorſe he could take the <hi>Philippians</hi> by the hand, and lead them to the Practice of every good work, by the conduct of his own Example; <hi>Brethren be ye follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers together of me, and mark them which walk ſo, as ye have us for an example,</hi> Phil. 3.17. And in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to theſe, he appeals to their own Conſciences, to judge in what manner of Converſation he walked among them, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.1.10. <hi>Your ſelves, Brethren,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:103379:23"/>know our entrance unto you, and ye are Witneſſes, and God alſo, how juſtly, and holily, and unblameably, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved our ſelves among you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Jub. Dei. <hi>P. 78.</hi>
               </note> for which reaſon <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian</hi> ſo highly and deſervedly commends him, <hi>Boni Domini bonus famulus, &amp; ſingularis Magiſtri praeclarus imitator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Brethren, we ſee our Calling; and are we Conſcientious in the management of it? We have heard our Profeſſion; and are our Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices anſwerable to it? We cannot, I am ſure, be ignorant of thoſe Arguments, that oblige our Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and do they preſwade us to a conſtant Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Obedience? Or are not the beſt of us too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſerious in the work of the Miniſtry; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our labours the leſs ſucceſsful Do we perſuade our People in the Myſteries of Godlineſs, and preſs them to unfeigned Repentance, and uniform Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Laws of Heaven, as men that know the terrors of the Lord, and believe without theſe things our Auditors ſhall periſh Eternally? Do we intreat, exhort and beſeech them as it were for their Lives and Salvation? Or do we count our Office a burden, and ſubſtituting others into our Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, are indifferent what Perſons labour in the Vineyard, ſo we may eat the Fruit thereof, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Profits in their appointed Seaſon? Do none of us by our ſcandalous lives diſgrace the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel we Preach, and ſo offend our weaker Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, by laying a ſtumbling Block in their way to Heaven, and ſcandalizing them by our licentious Courſes?</p>
            <p>I come not into this place to Caluminate any, much leſs to accuſe my Fathers, and my Brethren; this
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:103379:24"/>work I refer to the ſcrutiny of every mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and the Inquiſition of our Spiritual Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. And I heartily wiſh that every Miniſter in this Aſſembly after the ſtricteſt Examination will be found to have approved himſelf a faithfull and wiſe Steward in the Houſe of God; that our care is to rertench the ſins and impieties, and to repair the Schiſms and Diviſions in the places were we live: that we are obedient to the voice of our exact Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to her Laws and Canons, and Brotherly kindneſs to one another; that in our Inſtructions and Exhortations, we diſplay the odious Nature of ſin in its proper colours, that ſinners may bluſh, and be aſhamed at their prophane and vicious courſes: And uſe the moſt prevalent Rhetorick to ſet forth Vertue to the life, to repreſent it with our utmoſt skill in the moſt amiable and lovely attire, that men may be drawn as with Cords of love to Court and embrace her; and above all theſe things, that we keep our ſelves unſpotted from the ſins of the World, for hereunto are we called, to be blameleſs and harmleſs, as the Sons of God, without rebuke, that our Converſations may be living Sermons, and our Sermons the lively Oracles of God.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the qualifications to make us faithfull Stewards in the Church of God: We muſt be Wiſe to underſtand the Myſteries of Religion, leſt we be deceived by the Stratagems and Sophiſtry of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſters; and Faithfull, leſt we ſeduce and delude others: We muſt be Learned in the word of God, that in our Doctrines we may ſhew Incorruptneſs, Gravity, Sincerity, and found ſpeech, that cannot be condemned; and Conſcientious in Preaching the ſame,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:103379:24"/>that he who is of the contrary part may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; and thoſe that gainſay the faithfull Word of God, by the ſoundneſs of our Doctrines and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of our Labours may be convinc'd. Who then is a faithful and wiſe Servant, whom his Lord hath made Ruler over his Houſhold to give them meat in due Seaſon; <hi>Bleſſed is that Servant, whom his Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing: For he ſhall ſay unto him, Well done thou good and faithfull Servant, thou haſt been faithfull over a few things, I will make thee Ruler over many things; enter thou into the Joy of thy Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
